<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some remarks upon government, and particularly upon the establishment of the English monarchy relating to this present juncture in two letters / written by and to a member of the great convention, holden at Westminster the 22nd of January, 1689.</title>
            <author>A. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B31</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2761</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13174578</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13174578</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98346</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28308)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98346)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 445:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some remarks upon government, and particularly upon the establishment of the English monarchy relating to this present juncture in two letters / written by and to a member of the great convention, holden at Westminster the 22nd of January, 1689.</title>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
                  <author>N. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>First letter signed: A. B.; "The Answer", p. 3-28, signed: N. T.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98346:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98346:1"/>
            <head>Some REMARKS upon GOVERNMENT, And particularly upon the ESTABLISHMENT Of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> MONARCHY Relating to this preſent Juncture.</head>
            <head type="sub">In Two LETTERS, Written by, and to a Member of the Great CONVENTION, holden at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the 22d. of <hi>January,</hi> 1688/9.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU have been highly Obliging in the frequent Accounts you ſent me of Affairs, in this Great and Extraordinary Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I was once very diffident, and could ſcarcely conceive that the <hi>States of Holland,</hi> or <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> could have attempted ſo Expenſive, and ſo Hazardous an Undertaking out of pure Generoſity, meerly for our Sakes, and for the Re-eſtabliſhment of our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> which did both equally Labour under the Preſſures of an Ill Adminiſtration, and ſeem'd to draw towards their laſt <hi>Periods.</hi> I knew the <hi>States</hi> had the Character of preferring their own, before any other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt whatſoever, and the <hi>Prince</hi> had the Reputation of ſetting a duo Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon <hi>That</hi> which creates and proportions the Value of all things elſe. The Enterprize I lookt upon, as very Expenſive in its Methods, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain in its Accompliſhment, which made me proue to believe that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more lay coucht in this Vaſt Undertaking, than was expreſt in the <hi>Prince's</hi> Declaration; But ſince His arrival and coming to <hi>London,</hi> I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98346:2"/>perceive He has, upon all Occaſions, carry'd Himſelf with that wonderful Modeſty, with ſuch an unparallel'd Care and Tenderneſs of our <hi>Laws, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> and adheres ſo Reſolutely to every Particular in His Declaration, that I cannot but eſteem theſe to be His Nobleſt Trophies: And that which crowns thoſe Succeſſes which have crown'd His Generous and Pious Undertakings. His perſiſting to referr all to the Impartial Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> to Do and Eſtabliſh ſuch Matters, either in His, their Own, or the Kings behalf, as they ſhall think fit, even then, when Honor and Power ſpread their Perſwaſives before Him to do otherwiſe, is ſo great a Thing that it exceeds all His other Glories, and ſtrikes the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders with nothing leſs than Amazement. I do more rejoyce than wonder at the Unanimous Concurrence which has hitherto been maintain'd between the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> Aſſembled in Councel, and indeed in the Wiſhes &amp; Deſires of all the People in General: It is what this Juncture does highly require, and what the <hi>Prince's</hi> Conduct does Oblige. We are very buſie here in the Countrey in Electing Members for the Great Convention which is to ſit in <hi>January,</hi> and I think the Lot will fall on me to ſerve for my Neighbouring Borough. You know I was never fond of Buſineſs or Trouble, and truly Age ſeems now to have ſign'd my Writ of Eaſe. I alſo always cheriſht ſome <hi>Cynical</hi> Notions, which made me very much ſlight and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard the Honours and Flatulencies of a giddy World: But the thoughts of being one of the Great Planters of a Government which ſhall laſt for Ages, and perhaps till Time has run out its laſt Minutes, is no Ordinary thing. This thought alone has envigorated my Age and baffled my Philoſophy, ſo that you may expect to ſee me in <hi>London</hi> about the 22d. of <hi>January</hi> next; and in the mean time, if you will favour me with your Thoughts and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Affairs, and what Underſtanding Men do think will, or ought to be the Iſſue and Conſequence of this great Revolution, you will very conſiderably add to the many Kindneſſe conferred upon</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>SIR,</hi> Your aſſured Friend and humble Servant <hi>A. B.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98346:2"/>
               <head>The Anſwer.</head>
               <p>YOurs (thô it bore and early Date, yet) came not to my hands till laſt <hi>Friday.</hi> I am very glad that my ſlender Services have prov'd upon any account acceptable to you. I never thought my ſelf qualified to pry into the Receſſes of Government, or the privacies of a King: What I acquainted you with, was little more than what was publickly diſcours'd of in Coffee-Houſes: But indeed ſuch was the Management of Affairs during our late King's Supremacy, That his moſt private Councels prov'd generally the next days Table-talk, for as they were ſhallow, ſo was the bottom of them diſcoverable to every common Eye. The <hi>Prince</hi> has per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, with more Courage than Caution, and a great Zeal for the Proteſtant Intereſt, then Care of His own particular Concerns, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken mighty Things for us, and run ſuch Riſques in the Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of them, which Story can ſcarcely parallel. But what the ſequel of this will be, I muſt leave to <hi>Aſtrology.</hi> 'Tis true, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſeem to be Unanimous to a wonder, and yet there are a <hi>Sett</hi> of Men in this Nation whom nothing will ſatisfie but to Lord it over their Brethren: Theſe do ſtill labour under ſome Diſcompoſures, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, in no reſpect diſoblig'd, yet fearing they may receive a Cruſh in this great <hi>Turn,</hi> do by their Sourneſs and Diſcontent rather aſſiſt and further their fate, than anticipate and prevent it. The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diſſenters are not eſteem'd, by Computations which have been formerly made, to amount to more than a 25th. part of the Nation, the Church of <hi>England</hi> receiving all the reſt: This I do believe to be true, if the Church of <hi>England</hi> be taken in the moſt large and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Senſe, by including all ſuch as frequent the publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: But if we might ſuppoſe them in the ſame Circumſtances that Diſſenters were in, at the time of this Computation made, under the Frowns of the Court, and the power of the Laws, which like ſo many Billows, beat in againſt them; if thus we might be admitted to view them in Reverſe, I do believe their Numbers would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, or Scarcely equal thoſe of the Diſſenting party. There are but very few in the Nation would undergo Fines and Impriſonment for the ſake of the <hi>Surplice</hi> or <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi> The prevailing Opinion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98346:3"/>now in <hi>England</hi> is, <hi>Latitudinarian:</hi> Moſt Men are ſo far improv'd in their Judgments, as to believe, that Heaven is not entail'd upon any particular Opinion, and that either an Epiſcopal, or Presbyterial way of Worſhip, together with a due obſervation of the Rules of Morality, may ſerve well enough to carry them to Heaven, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Byaſs which enclines them to the one ſide or the other, being the Laws. <hi>Be ſubject to the Higher Powers, not for Wrath, but Conſcience,</hi> ſways the Scale and gives the caſting Vote in ſuch Things as are thought indifferent: This is it which crowds the Church, otherwiſe the Sarſnet Hood and Lawn Sleeves might be as deſtitute of Votaries, as the Long Cloak and Collar Band.</p>
               <p>Which may the ſucceeding Government will lean, I dare not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, but it is more than probable, That <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> in that ſtrictneſs in which it has of late Years excercis'd, ow'd its <hi>Continuance,</hi> as well as Originally its <hi>Being,</hi> to the King: His power and His purſe, has been liberally imploy'd in favour of the Church, and they as plentifully requited His Kindneſs, by their Doctrines of <hi>Jure Divino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience:</hi> So long as the King continued thus their Servant, He was in all Cauſes Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, their Supreme Head and Governour: But when the King became of another Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and they themſelves were likely to be ſqueez'd by the preſſures of their own Weighty Doctrines, then <hi>the Caſe Was</hi> immediately <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd</hi> and <hi>Plowdens Hogs could be no longer Treſpaſſers:</hi> They inſtantly chang'd their Note, and rang their Bells backward, for they were all on fire, and likely to be reduc'd to their original Duſt in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Fears of <hi>Popery</hi> was firſt the pretence of their diſſatisfactions: This way very plauſible, and ſeem'd once to give them an intereſt in the people: But ſurely now theſe Dangers are Remov'd; the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Intereſt is likely to ſettle upon firm Foundations, and the <hi>Prince</hi> ſeems well affected to their way of Worſhip, and ſignalizes His Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations by Communicating with them according to the Rights and Ceremonies of the Church, and yet they ſeem diſſatisfied, and are ſtill apprehenſive of Danger.</p>
               <p>What then can be the reaſon that this bright Hemiſphere ſhould thus be wrapt up in Clouds and Darkneſs? It muſt needs be this, That they have loſt, or are likely to loſe the King and Courts good Service employ'd in all or moſt of the former Parliaments ſo freely in their behalf. This in truth was the chief Pillar of their Church: That which firſt built, and afterwards ſupported it. Thô the <hi>Prince</hi> does ſufficiently approved of this Eſtabliſhment in His own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98346:3"/>Judgment, yet He is reſolved to call a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> being the purport of His <hi>Declaration,</hi> backt with many ſubſequent Promiſes and Aſſurances in which the People ſhall have freedom to Elect ſuch Perſons as are for the True Intereſt of the Nation, and not for the upholding a particular Intereſt or Faction There ſhall be no Elections either forc'd by Power, or brib'd by Treats; No falſe Returns, no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of <hi>Affections</hi> to determine according to the Court or Ch. of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Intereſt; No Parliamentary Penſions, nor Treats with Guinea's laid under their Plates to ſeduce them from their honeſt Principles and the Intereſt of their Country. The <hi>Prince</hi> abhors ſuch irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities: He deſires ſuch an Aſſembly may meet, as may truly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the People, to Enact and Eſtabliſh ſuch Laws and ſuch a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as may ſecure their Religion, Liberties and Properties, with the beſt advantage and ſecurity to the Nation that can be propoſed: And although the Church of <hi>England</hi> is hereby left deſtitute of that unfair and irregular advantage it firmly had from the King's power and aſſiſtance, yet I doubt not but this and ſucceeding Parliaments will Enact ſuch an Eſtabliſhment in the Church, as may very well agree with the honeſt deſires of the more moderate and pious Church-men.</p>
               <p>What the Civil Government will be, is more difficult to gueſs at, but I can tell you what it has been, and wherein it ſeems defective and requires ſome touches of your Legiſlative Skill to help it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut. This I am confident of, That if the Conſultations of this great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel does but produce what the Neceſſities of the People, and the Conveniencies which a well-ſetled State does require, the Alterations will be very conſiderable. 'Tis true, there is a Notion generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>Eng.</hi> that a <hi>Mixt Monarchy</hi> (juſt ſuch a one as ours is, and no other) muſt needs be the beſt of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that amongſt all others, none could boaſt of thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages as that of <hi>England.</hi> This fancy is ſo rivetted in the minds of the People (ſpread abroad and preacht up, only to keep the people in peace, and from endeavouring an Alteration, which could not be effected without the Inconveniencies of the Sword) that I do believe All things will again ſettle upon its old <hi>Baſis,</hi> and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be rebuilt with all its irregularies. However, becauſe I underſtand you are in election to be one of Thoſe, from whom ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages muſt derive their Happineſs or Miſery, I will make uſe of the Liberty you have given me, to expreſs my Sentiments in this mighty Affair, in order to which I will in the firſt place acquaint you with my Notions of Government in general, and afterwards will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98346:4"/>deſcend to Particulars; And to our preſent Caſe as it now lies:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Government is a Power whereby a Community of Men are kept in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, diſpoſed to act conformably to their Natures, and to the common advantage of the whole Body Politick.</hi> This Power is ſometimes plac'd in one ſingle Perſon, and then it is <hi>Monarchy:</hi> Sometimes in a ſelect number of the <hi>Chiefs,</hi> when it aſſumes the name of <hi>Aristocracy;</hi> And ſometimes in the whole Body of the People, which is called <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy.</hi> But of theſe three <hi>Primatives,</hi> there are ſeveral Derivatives, Compounds, and Variations.</p>
               <p>The firſt, <hi>Mageſtracy,</hi> I do allow to be grounded in Nature, and the firſt <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to be a <hi>Genarcha,</hi> or Patriarch, who rul'd over Families of his own Extraction, and Citties of his natural Generation. It was in this ſenſe that the Fifth Commandment was given; and it was from hence that Men grew up into Citties, Kingdoms, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, and therefore the Laws to regulate them ought to be ſuch as are apt and fit to govern Families, for the preſervation of their <hi>Peace, Libertys</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> not to bind them to perpetual Slavery and Vaſſalage. So alſo, the Submiſſions due from the People to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power, are in their nature filial, not ſervile, as proceeding rather from Love and Gratitude, for protection given, than for fear of the Rod hanging over their Backs, which ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed only to prevent a common Inconveniency. But this Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Government, continues no longer than the Patriarch holds a power over his Family, to puniſh ſuch offences in particular perſons, as might otherwiſe (if allowed of) obſtruct the common Intereſt; and to protect the whole Body and every individual in their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and acquir'd Rights, both from Domeſtick and Forreign Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: For when the natural power of one or more in Conjunction ſhall exceed that of the Patriarch, or Father of the Family, this for of Government is ſo far diſſolved, that if they pleaſe and find it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, they may reaſſume their natural Freedom, or again engag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſame Family, by Pact or promiſe, or elſe leave it, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> compact with others, ſubmit to what Laws or Meaſures of Livin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> together in a Comunity they think fit. He that will make t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> natural <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> more Sacred than this, may at laſt commit Idol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and fall down to worſhip.</p>
               <p>But this is not the State of any Nation or People now under Heaven. We are all ſhufled and blended together, ſo that we ſtand not Ori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally aſſociated to any Magiſtrate out of natural Duty, but out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mutual fear of each other, which to avoid, produc'd, theſe civil Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98346:4"/>by which the World is now Governed. Thus being ſeparated from our Families, each Man has a right by nature to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which ſuppoſes his primary Allegeance now due to himſelf: He has farther an equal right with all others to all things neceſſary for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation, &amp; an abſolute right in his own perſon; &amp; having thus a <hi>mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um jus</hi> in both, he is fitted for mutual Compact with others. 'Tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that Nature, thô She did provide for Mankind in its tender help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and unexperienced years, a natural Governour and Protector, yet being withdrawn from that Power and Subjection, it falls into a ſtate of War, which was the Condition of the World in thoſe Times, which Hiſtorians call Heroical: When <hi>Nimrod</hi> obtained the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the ſtouteſt Hunter, and <hi>Hercules</hi> travelled to tame Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Uſurpers.</p>
               <p>The Patriarchal Government being at an end, and the People being now left in a ſtate of War, occaſioned by the Univerſal Right that every man had to every thing, the Government that ſucceeded was accordingly Martial and Warlike, and their Governours were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Generals than Kings, and like them, Arbitrary and Unlimited. In this ſtate the Chief Magiſtrate was properly and Originally called <hi>Tyrannus;</hi> but Luſt, Ambition, and Avarice being the uſual atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of abſolute power, did too far prevail, to the prejudice of thoſe in Subjection, that both the Perſon and Title of ſuch Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in time became odious and contemptible. It was for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his life of <hi>Timoleon,</hi> affirms that over a Tyrant, every man is a Judge, and may be an Executioner; and <hi>Plato</hi> in his Common-wealth, delineates a Tyrant amongſt his Subjects by a Woolf amongſt the Flock, plac'd there rather to devour than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them.</p>
               <p>But the World ſoon grew weary of this Courſe of Life, and by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience found that Compact was more apt for the Coalition of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties than mere Power; which is the cauſe, That in the more civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd and cultivated parts of the Earth, this ſort of Government is very rare and unuſual, unleſs ſent by the Supream <hi>Power</hi> of Heaven and Earth for the puniſhment of a People for ſome Sins committed, that thereby they may be compell'd like the mute Fiſh in the Goſpel, to bring their Penny unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and after pay their Lives for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution: And it is obſervable that it prevails principally, and is no where elſe willingly allowed of, but where Idolatry and Invincible Ignorance are the National Sins.</p>
               <p>This Tyranical Government, or State of War, being found un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98346:5"/>in many places, and more intollerable than the Patriarchal Government in which they were firſt engaged, and alſo finding that there is now no Father of the Country, in a natural Senſe: The Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as becoming Orphans, chooſe <hi>One</hi> or <hi>More</hi> to be their Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, which in ſeveral Countries goes under ſeveral Denominations. Thus the People are in the ſtate of Pupillage, and as a <hi>Minor</hi> cannot make a Contract to his prejudice, ſo we may conclude, that the People may meliorate their Condition by Compact, but cannot make it worſe; and therefore it may with much more reaſon be allowed, that ſuch Conceſſions which are made by them, and which infringe or derogate from their natural Rights ſhould be void, than that what a Prince grants to his People out of his Prerogative (tho' for their better Government and well Being, for which alone Prerogative was firſt given and intended) ſhould be null and of no validity, which ſome Preſidents in our preſent Eſtabliſhment ſeem to countenance and abet. Thus all Governments in the ſame degrees that they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from Patriarchal and Tyrannical muſt derive their Originals from Compact, and the Governour muſt neceſſarily derive his Power from and by, the mutual Conſent of the People he governs; unleſs God does himſelf immediately appoint a Magiſtrate, and even then the People have uſually confirm'd, as in the caſe of <hi>Saul.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. So of <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>I cannot but with <hi>Grotius</hi> believe, that <hi>Salus populi est Suprema Lex.</hi> Nor did <hi>Junius Brutus</hi> err in affirming that, <hi>Imperii finis unicus eſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli Utilitas.</hi> But on the contrary to imagine the People to be made for their King, and that a Million of Souls ſhould be Born Slaves and Vaſſals to the Luſt and Tyrrany of one Man, who by nature is no more than their fellow Creature, made of the ſame mold, and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon the ſame level with themſelves, is nonſenſe and directly contradictory to the true notion of Government it ſelf. In all States and Kingdoms whoſe Government is by Compact, the King cannot be ſuppoſed to be any thing more than an Officer, elected and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the People to preſerve the Government, and therefore the People muſt neceſſarily be ſuppoſed to have ſtill a Reſerve of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in extraordinary Exigences above the King. <hi>Quicquid efficit Tale eſt magis tale.</hi> Their Conceſſions cannot extend farther than for their own preſervation, and when that ceaſes, the Grant determines Our General and Original Rights cannot totally be ſwallowed up by any Compact that can be made to ſettle Liberty and Property, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is all that was Natural now made Civil; wherefore that old Law
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98346:5"/>was but old Reaſon. <hi>Quod populus poſtremum jubet id ratum eſto.</hi> Upon this Account the People in notorious caſes, do themſelves become the Accuſer, Judge, and Executioner; it being but reaſon that in ſuch Caſes they ſhould be allowed this priviledge; for as every man is the beſt Judge of his own health, and how ſuch and ſuch Meats and Medicines aſſiſts and helps the health and vigor of his Body; ſo in the <hi>Body Politick,</hi> the People muſt be Judge how this or that Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or Law agrees with their Conſtitution, and Contributes to their Health, Peace, and Welfare. In the 17th. of <hi>Deut.</hi> and the 14th. <hi>v.</hi> God leaves the Election of a King abſolutely to the People, and puts it into their choice whether they will have a King or not, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they pleaſed to ſet over them (provided he were choſen from among their Brethren) ſhould be their King. Thus before <hi>Davids</hi> Inauguration, <hi>The People made a league with him,</hi> 2. Sam. 5.3. v. And by this they reſtrained and bound him up as they thought fit: And he who in any ſettled legal Government, arrogates to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and other Supremacy over all or any part of his Brethren, other than what is immediately appointed by God, or claimed from the People, breaks thoſe Bonds and Limits which they have ſet; and is as Civilians diſtinguiſh, <hi>Tyrannus exercitio,</hi> though not <hi>Titulo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Supream, Abſolute, and Arbitrary Power, is eſſentially neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in all Governments whatſoever, whether <hi>Monarchial, Aristo-critical,</hi> or <hi>Democritical,</hi> in reſpect of which, theſe three diſtinct Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies differ no otherwiſe than as a Guinea from twenty Shillings, or forty Sixpences, which put together are equivalent one to the other: Thus the Supream Acts of all Governments are the ſame, for no State can go higher (nor ought to deſcend lower) than <hi>1ſt.</hi> to be able to redreſs a grievance, by making or repealing a Law. <hi>2ly.</hi> to have the power of War and Peace, <hi>3ly.</hi> to judge of Life and Death, and <hi>4ly.</hi> to fix and Appeals in it ſelf. So alſo if a mixture be made of theſe three Governments, yet it makes no change as to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of a Supream Act; for they who limit one another, are yet Copartners and do the ſame thing together which one alone doth Legiſlatively: And as the prudence and foreſight of the firſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of theſe various Conſtitutions, ſaw any advantage or inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency peculiar to the people, place, or time they liv'd in, ſo they accordingly made various and ſuitable proviſions and Laws, to aſſiſt the Good and to divert the Evil. Upon this account there are few Governments but have ſome things woven into their Conſtitution pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to themſelves. In <hi>Poland</hi> where the Monarchy is Elective, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98346:6"/>the Prince bound to obſerve the Laws, any Gentleman may ſafely and freely accuſe his Prince. In <hi>Arragon</hi> the Chief Juſtice has a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunition power. In <hi>Venice</hi> the Duke ſtirs not out of the City with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leave, and is made ſo much greater then any of the reſt, only to allay the growth of Ambition in any one beſides. In the form of Tranſactions, Moſt do follow the Plurality of Sufferage, but in ſeveral ways: In the Senate of <hi>Venice</hi> in many Caſes there muſt be a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of three parts of four. In the Conclave of <hi>Rome</hi> at the Election of the Pope, two parts of three muſt concur: In the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory the Pope alone carries it againſt all the Council of Cardinals. In the Convention in <hi>Poland, Potior est Conditio Negantis,</hi> One Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative hinders all proceedings in the moſt important Affairs. In <hi>Holland</hi> the States General of the Provinces have but ſeven Votes in all, and theſe obliging according to the Plurality of Sufferage, but the number of States ſent to manage the Intereſt of their ſingle and Provincial Votes are unlimitted; and as the reſpective Provinces pleaſe to Delegate; wherefore their Votes may be more properly termed local than perſonal; but with us in <hi>England</hi> Votes are merely perſonal; for as we repreſent not Provinces or Places diſtinctly Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream, but mixtly together; ſo the odd Vote carries all; by which it may happen that one man may make or deſtroy the beſt Law that ever was. From theſe particulars you may collect the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are in Government, inſtituted according to the different No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the firſt Founders, and the Circumſtances and Temper of the People Govern'd.</p>
               <p>Monarchy veſted with the moſt abſolute powers that either Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion or Conqueſt can create I eſteem the beſt of Governments, but that only happens when it repreſents God more in his <hi>Juſtice</hi> than <hi>Singularity;</hi> and when Mercy is the Ornament as well as Power the ſupporters of his Throne: In ſuch a Government under a Prince whoſe Goodneſs and Wiſdom runs in equal paralells with his power and greatneſs, the people are happy and ſecure, whilſt their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours live in fear and ſubjection, His Councils are private, and the Execution of them ſuddain, without which no great enterpriſe can be ſucceſsful: To ſuch a King is applicable the Anſwer which was made to this Queſtion upon <hi>Paſquill</hi> in <hi>Rome, Quid eſt Prerogativa Regis:</hi> The Reply being <hi>in optimo Rege nihil nimis, in Malo Omne Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum.</hi> But to take a view of this Government in its dark ſide, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Child, Fool, or vitious Prince, nothing carries ſuch an aſpect of Horror and Miſery to the poor Wretches who live under it: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98346:6"/>if we conſider that the generality of Men, when let looſe to their natural, or rather corrupted Inclinations, are much more apt to lean towards Tyranny and Oppreſſion, than to ſuch Methods as may promote their Peoples Happineſs, I think this ſort of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by no means deſirable. It does at the beſt but keep the State which is directed by it, in a fluctuating and unſetled condition. It ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the Reign of a Warlike and Ambitious Prince, like the Sea in a Storm, rowls in with rage, and Fury upon a Neighbouring Shoar, and again under the Tuition of another who is of a weak and puſillanimous ſpirit, it moulders and gives way to the loſs of all its former Acquiſitions, ſo that the Ballance of the Kingdom is never at a ſtand, the Scale moving ſometimes upwards, and anon down again, and the People conſequently kept in a rowling, unſetled condition, poor, miſerable, and uneaſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> is compoſed by a ſelect number of the Chiefs of the People to Govern the Reſt, and ſtands like a Moderatour between the Exceſſes of Kingly and Popular Power: But this Mixture often produces Monſters, and as as the greateſt Storms are form'd in the Middle Religion, ſo the Bloodieſt Commotions are rais'd in this State, though moſt Temperate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Democracy</hi> does properly and naturally reduce all to equality, and moſt carefully conſults the Peoples Liberty and Property, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, it obliges every Man to hold his Neighbours hand, and when it falls, it does with great difficulty recover its feet again. 'Tis true, that Monarchies are more Quick and Expeditious in their Attempts, but Common-Wealths, as they are more ſlow, ſo they are more ſure, and in regard that their Councils are more publick, ſo are they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally more Honeſt and juſtifiable. Common-wealths are not like Monarchies, ſubject to the inconveniencies of Evil Council or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption where the Prince's perſonal folly or ambition, the Commands of an Imperious Wife, or the Flatteries of a Fawning Courtezan, may in a minute overthrow a People and Kingdom. We have found it by ſad Experience, practiſed at home, where a Chamber-Maid has prevail'd with her Miſtreſs, and ſhe again by a Kiſs or Smile with the Monarch; and we alſo owe all our preſent Diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſures to the Directions of a Zealous Prieſt, manag'd by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of a Commanding Queen. We are alſo ſufficiently ſenſible of the great Unhappineſs that befalls a people living under a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, in having their Prince of a Religion different from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: But this Inconvenience can never befall a Common-wealth,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98346:7"/>it being impoſſible to change, alter, or introduce any new Religion by ſuch a Government, but ſuch as the greater part of the people embrace, and are willing to receive. But in Monarchies the King being but one perſon, may in that reſpect be more eaſily and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſeduc'd, both to his own and his peoples irreparable Injury.</p>
               <p>The Eaſtern Countries which lye under the Courſe of the Sun, as <hi>Perſia, Turky, Africa, Peru,</hi> and <hi>Mexico,</hi> are moſt diſpos'd to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies, in which latter Quarter of the World the people are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Govern'd by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who are by fits in the Exceſſes of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Cruelty, than by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> whoſe Government is of a more even Temper. But in <hi>Europe</hi> and nearer the Pole, the people are diſpos'd more to Republicks, temper'd by fundamental Laws. <hi>Nec totam ſervitutem pati poſſunt nec, totam Libertatem.</hi> Sir <hi>William Temple,</hi> whoſe inſight in the Conſtitutions of States and Kingdoms, may deſervedly give him a deciſive Vote, tells, us, That <hi>Monarchies do indeed ſeem moſt Natural, but Common-Wealths the more Artificial ſorts of Government;</hi> which was but a modeſt way of giving his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage for the laſt, for Art always corrects the defects of Nature, and polliſhes it up to a greater Luſtre: But when all is done, we find it experimentally true, that all Government's like all ſublunary things beſides, have their Defects: Nature in every part is ſick, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can find reſt in no poſture: Humane Laws grow out of Vices, which gives to every Government a tincture of Corruption.</p>
               <p>That the Government of <hi>England</hi> was originally and always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame conſtitution that now, or of late it did appear to be, I cannot conceive, though Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> and ſome others, do ſeem with much earneſtneſs to contend for it. I am of opinion, that like <hi>Epicurus</hi> his World, it is grown by Chance and Time to what it now is or lately was, by various Concuſſions and Confluence of People, Intereſts, Factions, and Laws, like ſo many Attoms of different ſhapes and diſpoſures, ſpringing from meer Accident in ſeveral Ages; for where there are Men, there will be alſo Intereſts, which creates Factions and Parties, and theſe, as they prevail, or are ſuppreſt, produce Laws for or againſt them, which ſo far alters the former Government, as new Laws are introduc'd in the room and place of old ones which were thought fit to be Repealed and Abrogated.</p>
               <p>Althô ſome Governments ſeem to be built upon firmer and more unalterable Foundations than others, yet there is none but ought to adapt it ſelf to the Circumſtances and Diſpoſition of the People Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd, and as theſe do daily change, ſo ought the Government to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98346:7"/>ſhift and tack with them, that it may the better hit with the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and changing Circumſtance of thoſe for whom it was firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Property is founded in Dominion,</hi> I look upon to be a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Truth, for Naturally in the ſame degree that a Man has a Right and poſſeſſion in a thing, he muſt neceſſarily have the Power and Dominion over it; To argue or defend the contrary, is as great an abſurdity in Nature, as to ſay the Fire muſt be hot, and yet not burn ſuch Cumbuſtibles as are caſt into it. It is upon this account that the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> is ſo Deſpotick in his Government, for by the Conſtitutions of that State all Lands are in the Crown, none hold longer than during pleaſure, or for Life, and then their Lands revert to him that gave them. For the ſame reaſon, in the days of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Ignorance and Poverty, when Arts and Learning were ſtrangers to the Land, and the people were ſcarcely removed from their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive eſtate of Nature and War, when every man had a univerſal Right to all things, and no man could by a peculiar property pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to a Poſſeſſion longer then his Sword and Bow could maintain it; Then I ſay were our Governours like <hi>Generals,</hi> abſolure and unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. 'Tis true indeed, we have ſome dark ſhadows of Laws and Councils, then in uſe, which our Governours thought fit, as they ſaw occaſion to make uſe of; and we alſo find the People ſometimes diſſatisfied, treating their Magiſtrate with much Roughneſs and ill Uſage upon his Male Adminiſtration; yet this does not at all argue that their Governours were limitted and bound up by Laws, as now they are: Theſe things are all practiz'd in <hi>France, Turky,</hi> and the moſt Arbitrary Monarchies in the World. Without Laws and Methods, ſuch as theſe, one Man is not able to govern Millions, and therefore <hi>Moſes,</hi> who under <hi>God,</hi> was Abſolute and Arbitrary, was neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to appoint certain Rules and Methods, and to admit of others into the Government with him, as Aſſiſtants, by their Councel and Advice, the Work being too great for one Man to diſcharge. It was from the King's abſolute Property in the Lands of <hi>England</hi> (which in thoſe Times none could pretend to but by and through him who held the Sword) as well as from his power over the Laws that our old Tenures ſprung of Knight ſervice, <hi>Serjeantry,</hi> Eſcuage, Socage, Villenage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then were all Tenures <hi>ſervile,</hi> and all Perſons held mediately or immediately from the King, which our Law-Books tell us, we ſtill do; but there was a vaſt difference between our then, and preſent Holdings, the firſt being by actual Services paid; theſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98346:8"/>now being only Nominal and Titular: To hold in <hi>Socage,</hi> is by the ſervice of the Plow, (as almoſt all perſons are ſaid to do) The Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was in old Times actually bound to Plow the Lords Lands, in conſideration of which Service, he granted to his Plow-man, inſtead of Wages, to hold another piece of Land to his own proper uſe; but now, though the Tenure does nominally remain, yet the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is abſolute; every Man being now become, by the circular motions of Chance or Providence, his own Lord, and his own Plow-man: His Property and Poſſeſſion makes him the Lord over thoſe Glebes which his Neceſſity (derived from his Anceſtor <hi>Adams</hi> Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion) makes him Till.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Governments which ſucceeded the <hi>Patriarchal,</hi> were all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary; all people being then left by Nature in a ſtate of War; but ſome Countries ripening into Prudence and Knowledge ſooner than others, they alſo ſooner betook themſelves to Compact, and to ſuch Methods of living, as might be for their Common Advantage. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe, <hi>England</hi> was none of the earlieſt Reformers, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued long after <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> in that Natural ſtate that the firſt Fathers of Families leſt it: and there was reaſon for it in reſpect it was an Iſland, and (in thoſe Times, when <hi>Navigation</hi> was in a great degree a ſtranger to the World) not ſo apt for Commerce or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with other Countries which were more civilized; they had then no Government but what conduc'd to War, and no other King but a General. <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Commentaries, telis us, that he found the <hi>Brittains,</hi> poor, ignorant, and deſtitute of Laws, but he alſo gives them the Character of a People diſpos'd to War, <hi>Brittannnos in Bello promptos &amp; in Armis expertes:</hi> All things (as in the ſtate of Nature) were in Common, even to their Wives and Children: But the <hi>Romans</hi> having given them a taſte of the ſweetneſs and advantage of Government, they ſoon after began (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> in his Annals ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us) to make Application to their General, to protect and defend them, by his Power and Strength, in the peaceable enjoyment of certain proportions and allotments of Land, againſt all Invaders; In lieu of which Protection to them and their Heirs, they promiſe and ſwear to him and his Heirs, certain Services, together with Homage and Fealty. With this Notion of <hi>Tacitus, Bide</hi> ſeems to concur in the 4th. Book of his Hiſtory, where he ſays, That Generals and Kings were amongſt the <hi>Brittains</hi> as Terms Univocal, for Kings went al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways out to Battle in times of War, and in Peace, exercis'd the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative power at home: And <hi>Ammianus</hi> in his 15th. Book, is more
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98346:8"/>plain and poſitive, for he tells us, That <hi>Brittanni nulla ſeparali frueban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur poſſeſſione, niſi Principis conceſſu &amp; poteſtate defendantur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence it may be reaſonably allowed, that <hi>England</hi> was firſt Governed by an abſolute Power, not from the Election of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor by Conqueſt, but from the Temper, Diſpoſition, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of that Age of the World in which moſt Countries lay under the ſame ſort of Government, and more eſpecially by their Ignorance of better methods, which continued longer in Iſlands by reaſon of the difficulty of Commerce, than in Continents where a Correſpondence was then more eaſily maintained. It is undoubtedly from this bottom, that the People of <hi>England</hi> are ſtill ſuppoſed to hold all their Lands mediately or immediately from the King, and 'tis perhaps from hence that ſo many Commons and Waſts ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unincloſed, and that Waiſs, Strays, Wrecks, Waſts, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, in which no man can lay a particular propriety, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be in the Crown.</p>
               <p>Upon theſe reaſons I conclude, that the property of all the Lands here in <hi>England</hi> being originally in no particular perſon, muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily (as the Law ſtill is in ſuch Caſes) reſt in the King, and thoſe that held from or by his power, neither had or could have any right againſt that power by which they held, but only againſt others that were in a level with themſelves.</p>
               <p>How many theſe Landed Men Originally were, or what ſepe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate proportions were alloted to them, whether the quantity of a County, Hundred, or Tything, or whether their Allotments were according to the largneſs of their reſpective Families, or their Princes favour, I cannot ſay: But theſe Proprietors were probably the <hi>Pares Regni,</hi> or ſuch as afterwards, by the growth of Laws and the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of Ignorance, became by a ſettled and uncontroulable right, the Peers and Nobles of the Land; and having by their Princes permiſſive favour long enjoyed their Dignities and Poſſeſſions, they at laſt wrought them up to an Eſtabliſhment by Law, inſomuch that what was held before <hi>ad voluntatem Domini,</hi> is now made hereditary, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming only ſome ſmall Services and Acknowledgments to their King of General, ſome whereof were payable in times of War, as Knight Service, Eſcuage, petty Serjeanty, and grand Serjeanty, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in times of Peace, ſuch were Burgage, Villenage, Socage, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and Fealty.</p>
               <p>Thus did a part of the People firſt twiſt themſelves into a real Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty in part of the Lands of the Kingdom, and as the Prince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98346:9"/>kind and liberal, ſo did the numbers of theſe Proprietors increaſe, and their Properties grew more ſtrong and indefeaſable, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently their Power and Dominions; but the Prince on the other hand grows proportionably poorer and weaker, Both reſembling a Boat which riſes and falls with the flowing Element that bears it up. After this manner the Lords grew daily richer and ſtronger, till they had in a great meaſure, by their acquiſitions ſtrip'd the Crown of its chiefeſt Embelliſhments, and inveſted themſelves in much the better ſhare of the Lands of <hi>England:</hi> And their Power grew with their Property to that degree, that they who were Originally but Servants to the Prince, became now Maſters of the Nation. This, King <hi>John</hi> to his ſorrow, was ſufficiently ſenſible of in his Barons War; and it was from the Power of the Nobility alone that King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh did receive his Chaplet as well as Crown. He was a wiſe Prince, and from hence took an occaſion of Jealouſly, that the ſame Powers which rais'd and plac'd him in the Throne, might pull him down again and lay his Glories in the Duſt. To prevent therefore all Dangers which might ariſe from their growing Greatneſs, he firſt procures a Statute to be Enacted againſt Retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that the number of the Followers and Attendants of Noblemen might be retrench'd, for they did ſo far indulge the Vanity of a large Retinue in thoſe times, that their reſpective Trains were ſufficient for a Soveraign Prince's Guard. In the next place he procures the Statute of Fines to paſs both Houſes, whereby the Nobility got a power (which by the Common Law they had not) to cut of Entails, and thereby to ſell their Eſtates to the beſt Purchaſer. Before this Statute, and Eſtate in a Noblemans hand, might in ſome reſpect be ſaid to be in <hi>Mortmain,</hi> for by the Intail it was ſo bound up in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, that it grew almoſt irremoveable; and thus having a power to purchaſe but not to fell, their Poſſeſſions, and conſequently their Power grew daily greater, without a poſſibility of Diminution. But theſe Entails, as they were injurious to Trade and Induſtry, ſo by their Conſequences they were dangerous to Regall Authority, and therefore this Device was contriv'd to prevent both theſe Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies: and it did indeed prove very effectual in diveſting the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity both of their Property and Power, but at the ſame time it open'd a Door to the Commonalty, and gave them free acceſs to that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty and Dominion which the Nobility did by degrees part with: Nor did they neglect to improve this advantage they had got by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, Induſtry and Frugality, for in proceſs of Time they wound
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98346:9"/>themſelves into the better ſhare of thoſe Poſſeſſions which were firſt derived from the King to his Nobles, and from them thus to the Commons of the Nation.</p>
               <p>The Effect and Conſequence of theſe Acquiſitions, made by the Commonalty, were diſcover'd and fear'd by King <hi>James,</hi> but not felt till the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, who by an imprudent Conteſt with <hi>This</hi> Superior Power, was firſt depriv'd of his Crown, and afterwards of his Life. The yearly Rents of <hi>England</hi> (beſides the accrewing benefit of Trade, which is altogether in the hands of the Commonalty) amounts to 14 Millions <hi>per annum.</hi> Of this the King and Nobility both together hold not above one Million at the moſt, the King's Revenue being principally made up by the Exciſe and Cuſtoms, not by the Rents of Crown Lands; ſo that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains 13. ſhares of 14. of the Lands of <hi>England,</hi> and conſequently a proportionable ſhare of the Power in the Commons. But the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of our Government, as it now ſtands, placing the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the King, whilſt the Property is in the People, does in this commit a ſort of Violence upon Nature, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeperating thus the Soul from the Body, the Power from the Poſſeſſion: This it is which cauſes theſe frequent Diſtempers and Convulſions in the Body Politick; for Power is a ſort of Volatile Spirit which cannot ſubſiſt without a proper Vehicle to give in Body, and this muſt be Poſſeſſion, from which if it be once ſeparated, it immediately evaporates and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appears.</p>
               <p>Having hitherto trac'd the Government of <hi>England</hi> in its Originals and Procedures, I will farther take the liberty to advert ſome Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars as they ſeem now to ſtand in its preſent Conſtitution; and in the firſt place, I cannot think it ſo happy and well compos'd a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſo aptly ſuited to the preſent condition to the People, as moſt Men endeavour to repreſent it, for it ſeems in its Frame and Nature to be <hi>ſett</hi> to Factious Intereſts and Diſſentions, and thus it has been ever ſince the diſunion between Property and Power; the Court and Country Intereſts are no new nor unknown Terms to us, and have been managed and upheld by their reſpective Votaries (tho in ſome Kings Reigns with greater Spirit and Animoſity than in others) ever ſince, and for ſome time before the Barons Wars. The people have got the Poſſeſſion, and the King is entruſted with a power and prerogative over it, or at leaſt with ſo much, as may prove prejudicial to it. This Naturally creates Fears and Jealouſies, leaſt at any time the Prince by his power, ſhould invaded their Properties and abridge
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98346:10"/>their Liberties, upon which account his Prerogative is the <hi>White</hi> they level at, eſteeming it rather their Terror than their Security for which it was at firſt given and intended; and therefore when the people find an opportunity, either by their Prince's weakneſs, folly, or other unhappy circumſtances, they have uſually made breaches upon this Bulwark of the Crown, and by ſuch Sallies and Incurſions have got ground and advantage towards the farther ſecuring of thoſe Liberties and Properties they with ſo much Diligence and Reaſon endeavoured to provide for. So on the other ſide is the Prince jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his people, and is always fearful that they ſhould ſnatch this Rod which he holds over their Backs out of his hand; and to obviate this Evil, he is not without his Counter-deſigns alſo, and therefore ſpares neither Money nor Power in the Elections of Parliaments and Juries, to obtain ſuch perſons to be return'd, as for a Meſs of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge will ſell their Birth-right, and by advancing his Prerogative and lengthening his Scourge, are willing to ruine and undo their Country: And ſo it generally falls out, that when this <hi>power</hi> happens to fall into the management of an haughty daring Spirit, it breaks in upon the people, and endeavours to get again by Force, what his Anceſtors had given away by Flattery. Thus there is always a Tide of Ebb or Flow, the Scales rarely or never ſtanding even between the King and his People; and indeed the Conſtitution of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is ſuch, That Murmuring and Diſſention do naturally ſpring from it: the <hi>Ground</hi> is diſpos'd to produce ſuch Weeds, we are always engag'd in a ſort of Civil War, and in this reſpect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill in the ſame ſtate in which Nature left us. <hi>An Houſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided against it ſelf cannot ſtand,</hi> every Man has enough to do to defend his <hi>own</hi> from Domeſtick Invaders, and whilſt this <hi>Root</hi> of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is ſuffer'd to grow at Home, its impoſſible to do any thing that's Great abroad; every Deſign is poyſon'd with a Jealouſie in its Cradle, and it is enough to make the people ſuſpect it a Snake (thô the Skin and Flowers in which it lies be never ſo plauſible and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) if the King does but hand it to them. From hence it is that our Government always totter'd, twice fell down, and now lies in its primitve undigeſted <hi>Chaos,</hi> and he muſt be a greater Architect, than Perhaps our Nation can afford, to warrant its ſtanding above three ordinary Reigns, if it be rebuilt upon its old Foundations. An Expedient to prevent this Inconvenience, will be a proper Subject for this Great Convention.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98346:10"/>
               <p>Another thing not well conſiſtent with the Policy and Government of <hi>England,</hi> is the exceeding largeneſs of the Revenue of the Crown. In <hi>France</hi> indeed it is ſix times greater, that King being reputed to have 12. Millions, and the King of <hi>England</hi> but two: But we ſee the miſerable Effects of it, in the extreme Poverty and Vaſſallage of his people. 'Tis true, the Kings of <hi>England</hi> once had more, for they had in effect all, but then the people were but one remove from the ſtate of Nature, and the poſſeſſions are now got into the hands of the people, which they will be loath to part from, ſo that the Caſe is much alter'd; Whatſoever the Government of Heaven may be, yet on Earth in one State there cannot be two Equals, One muſt ſubmit and the other muſt Govern, or elſe there will be a conſtant War; and while the King has ſo great a Revenue as to be able to maintain a Standing Army, there ſtill remains ſo much of this Equality as will promote and maintain ſuch Differences as ought by no means to be allow'd of in a well conſtituted Government: But moreover, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by the preſent Conſtitution, are Sharers with the Prince in the Supreme and Legiſlative Power in Parliament, and 'tis by them that Grievances muſt be redreſt. It ought therefore in every Well-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Government to be provided for, that this Supreme and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Power may frequently, if not always, be in a capacity to Enact and Order ſuch things as tend to the Peoples Benefit and Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but in this, our Government is defective, it being in the Prince's power (as our Lawyers have generally determin'd) to keep off Parliaments as long as he pleaſes. And how is this defect remedied? Only by another, which on the other ſide they ſubject the Prince to, which is, by keeping him poor, that ſo his poverty may neceſſitate him to call frequent Parliaments. Thus by a mutual lameneſs or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity on both ſides, the Prince and People are become equal Matches, Both Cripples, not able to go forward in any great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes abroad, but to lie ſtruggling with each other at home. King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, had but 56000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> whole Revenue was but 160000 <hi>l.</hi> but ſome kind Parliaments (and ſuch they uſually are to exceſs, upon the firſt acceſſion of a King to the Throne) either brib'd by Smiles, or flatter'd by Hopes of private Gain, have thought fit to ſetter the Nation by advancing the Revenue to about two Millions <hi>per annum;</hi> ſo that now there is little hopes of meeting with thoſe advantages and opportunities of tacking their Grievances to a Money Bill, which formerly they uſe to do; though in truth, even then the State was in a dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98346:11"/>that could not have a Remedy at hand upon every Diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Malady which ſhould happen. This I think may not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly be eſteem'd a thing worthy of Your Thoughts to find a proper Expedient to redreſs it.</p>
               <p>Another Particular which I take to be one of the greateſt Sileciſms in Government imaginable is where the moſt Abſolute and Supreme power is yet without a Power to Remedy and Redreſs the Peoples Grievances: Thus it has been for many years adjudged to be by the Interpreters of our Laws and Government, the Judges. And to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate this by an Inſtance. Suppoſe the people are agriev'd, and want a law to ſet them Right; The King has no power to make it of himſelf, and till he thinks fit to call a Parliament, the people muſt ſtill continue ſubject to their Government: But perhaps the Kings Intereſt (which is unhappily divided from the peoples) forbids this Expedient; What ſhall be done? Why then let them ſtay and be ruin'd, till the King wants Money, which as the preſent Eeſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, will never be. But ſuppoſe a Parliament is called, and they in their proceedings happen to fret upon the Kings Prerogative, a Favourite evil Councellor, or ſome other Intereſt that the King has a mind to promote and protect, though never ſo oppoſite to that of the Nations, why then their Supreme and Legiſlative power is not worth a Ruſh, for the King, though he has no abſolute power him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet has a power above this, to deſtroy it by a Diſſolution or Prorogation when he pleaſes, and ſo like the Cat in the Manger, can neither eat Hay himſelf, nor ſuffer the Horſe to eat to whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs. This ſeems contrary to all the Rules of Art and Nature, and more Unintelligible than the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> or <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> for here the Supreme power is ſubject to an Inferior, and the King who is <hi>Minor Univerſis,</hi> yet is alſo <hi>Major</hi> and Superior to them; That Power which was given for the Protection of the People is their Deſtroyer, and the great and weighty Affairs of the Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſubject to the paſſions and humours of a ſingle Perſon. This I think I may ſafely affirm, That all Governments are built upon wrong bottoms, where there is not a Supreme and Abſolute Power, which may without Controll, and upon any ſuddain Occaſion or Emergency, alter, create, or repeal ſuch Laws as ſhall be thought by them neceſſary for the Peoples Good.</p>
               <p>Another thing that has been very incongruous and diſagreeable in our Eſtabliſhment is, That the Election of the Judges, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the pronouncing of the Law, ſhould be in the Kings Power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98346:11"/>If indeed he were a Third Perſon unconcern'd in point of Intereſt, this Method would be more tolerable; but being <hi>One</hi> that ſo often ſets up an Intereſt different from that of his People, and is ſubject to be ſeduc'd by the evil Councels of a Confeſſor, Miſs or Favourite, and the Peoples Rights hanging wholly upon the Lips of theſe twelve men in Scarlet, it is moſt fit they ſhould be choſen by Them who are chiefly concern'd, and for whoſe benefit and protection both the King and Laws were firſt made and intended, otherwiſe that very Prerogative, which was given to the King only for the better ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling him to act for the benefit of the People, may be (and often is) ſet up againſt them. It is contrary to all Rule, that in any Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie a Man ſhould be Judge in his own Caſe, But he in effect is ſo who has power to make or unmake the Judge at pleaſure: nor can this defect be well remedyed by granting their Commiſſions <hi>quam diu ſe bene geſſerint.</hi> This will only oblige a greater care in the firſt choice, that they may be ſuch as in their Principles will ſtand firm to the Kings Intereſt. The Honour and Income of a Judge to one that knows not how otherways to live is a violent Provocative; it is a ſort of lawful Bribery upon him to purſue his <hi>Maker</hi> and <hi>Deſtroyers</hi> Commands tho againſt all the Rules of Juſtice and Equity; <hi>ſelf Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> is his Warrant, binds him to a Complyance, and makes him think it more allowable to break his Oath then to deſtroy his Honour and the Intereſt of a young Favourite who makes hay with great diligence whilſt his Sun ſhines.</p>
               <p>I have often wondered at the unjuſt Cenſures of ſome in ſaying that our late King ſo often and ſo notoriouſly broke his word and promiſes to his People in not Governing them according to <hi>Law.</hi> For Inſtances, they urge His Diſpenſing with Statutes, and his hard Uſage of the Gentlemen in <hi>Maudlin</hi> Colledge, in both which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive he committed no breach of his Word or Promiſes if they be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſtrictly and in a literal ſenſe. This I think may eaſily be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted if it be conſider'd, That the preſent Laws and Conſtitutions of <hi>England</hi> are ſuch as do undoubtedly give the King a Power to make the Judge, and to the Judge a power to pronounce the Law. What he does judicially affirm is Law, and becomes from thenceforth the ſtrongeſt Preſident, the laſt Judgment being always eſteem'd the ſureſt and beſt Rule to go by: Now the King in both theſe tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons neither made or turnd out any Judges but in ſuch methods that former Judges had pronounc'd Lawful, nor did he do afterwards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98346:12"/>thing either in the caſe of <hi>Maudlin</hi> Colledge or the Diſpenſing Power, but with the Opinion and Concurrence of his Judges being the Method that our Eſtabliſhment and Laws in ſuch Caſes does direct.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a great Cry againſt the late Judges, for giving their Opinions, and pronouncing Judgments contrary to the Laws of the Land, and no other Fate muſt be their reward, but that of <hi>Treſilian</hi> and <hi>Belknap.</hi> It does, I muſt confeſs, ſeem very reaſonable, that Men, who by their Honour, Oaths and Rewards, were bound in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinguiſhably to adminiſter Juſtice, ſhould ſmart for thoſe Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencies by which ſo many Hundreds have been ruin'd and undone. But in the firſt place, let me know how a Judge can give his Opinion contrary to Law, whoſe very Opinion judicially given, by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of our Government, is Law it ſelf, and ſhall be deem'd a ſtronger Preſident in the point, than any other formerly given. And Secondly, If Judges muſt ſuffer for giving Sentence contrary to former Judgments, there is ſcarcely a <hi>Term</hi> paſſes even in the beſt of Times, but there are Offences committed by them of this kind. How ordinary is it for a Judge to give his Opinion in common Caſes contrary to his Brethren on the ſame Bench, and for one Court to reverſe the Judgments of another? And how full are the Law Books of Judgments and Opinions directly contrary to each other? The Law is not Mathematically demonſtrable, it is a Science which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Judgment and Opinion only of thoſe that are Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein, which we often find various and uncertain. Is not a Judge Sworn to act and determine according to his Opinion only, and who can pretend a power to direct and rectifie it, or to judge whether the Sentence given, was not according to his real judgment, ſince none can know his heart and thoughts but <hi>God:</hi> And ſuppoſe it could be prov'd by Demonſtration, that his Sentence or Opinion was not Law, this may proceed as well from his want of Knowledge as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and what Law is there to puniſh a Judges ignorance or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake? 'Tis hard that Men ſhould be deem'd guilty of a Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion where there is no Law, or condemn'd to puniſhment where there is no Tranſgreſſion. No, no, Thô our King was miſguided, and our Judges were corrupt, yet it is not at their doors, we muſt lay our Misfortunes but to the weakneſs of our Government, which gives a <hi>Looſe</hi> to theſe Inconveniencies, and which pins the Juſtice of the Nation upon the Frailties of a ſingle Man in ſo Arbitrary a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Opportunity makes a Thief, and theſe Meſhes in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98346:12"/>tempts the Miniſters thereof to ſlip through ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when a Bait lies on the other ſide to invite them to it. It is from this Root that all our late Miſcarriages ſprung; We ſuffer'd much, and yet it was all but little, if compar'd to that which was likely to befall us, had not Providence ſnatcht us by a Miracle from the Jaws of Miſery; and as it has deliver'd us from the Evil Adminiſtration of <hi>Law,</hi> ſo in ſome things I wiſh it would reſcue us from the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf, and ſo far change it, that for the future it may be no more ſubject to ſuch Shams and Deluſions, nor in a capacity thus to become an Acceſſory to its own Death.</p>
               <p>It ſeems farther very incongruous, That where Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is made up of two different Intereſts, as here it is, the abſolute power of Peace and War ſhould be only in the King, whilſt the power of maintaining it, continues in the People: For if the King ſhould be led aſide by a private Intereſt, and ſhould refuſe to make War in a time when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Safety and Honour of the Nation did wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon it; What a condition muſt the People then be in? Put the caſe, that before this our late but ſeaſonable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, the King, in whom this Power did reſide, ſhould have open'd the Gates of the Kingdom, our Harbours and Strengths (which are to protect us from Forreign Invaders) to a <hi>French,</hi> or <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army; Who durſt lift a hand to ſtop this inundation of Tyranny, without incurring the penalty of a Traytor: Nay they muſt farther be call'd Friends and Allies, even whilſt they pillage our Houſes, and hold their Knives to our Throats. This Branch of our Laws ſerves to <hi>cover</hi> the Landing of a Forreign Power, and ſo long to cheriſh and keep it warm, till like the Serpent in the Fable, it at laſt ſtings the improvident Benefactor to death.</p>
               <p>Another thing which highly requires Your Regulation, is the Elections for Parliament. 'Tis a great Blemiſh to our Government, that ſuch whoſe Place gives them the Title of <hi>Founders</hi> of our Laws, and <hi>Preſervers</hi> of our Liberties;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98346:13"/>and whoſe Reputation for Principles of Honour, Honeſty &amp; Prudence ſhould be beyond aſſault or cenſure, muſt yet be expos'd to a Neceſſity of doing ſuch things as are really mean and ſcandalous as well as expenſive, before they can get into a Capacity of doing their Country ſervice: for if ſuch things be not done, ſome Penſioner from Court bids higher, joſtles him our and gets thereby into a Power to put to Sale both the Laws and Liberties of his Country which he is willing to barter for the hopes of ſome Court Preferment, and the <hi>Euge</hi> of his great <hi>Maſter.</hi> In old times no perſon had an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting Vote in the Shire, who had not a Freehold of 40 <hi>s. per Ann.</hi> but I could eaſily demonſtrate 40 <hi>s.</hi> then, to be E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivolent in value to 40 <hi>l.</hi> now, for by the diſcovery of the Weſtern World, Gold and Silver is to that degree increas'd. Now if the number of Electors were reduc'd to thoſe only having Freeholds of 40 <hi>l. per An.</hi> theſe laviſh Expences would certainly ceaſe, and the Electors, though fewer in number, would be leſs apt to be led aſide by ſuch low and indirect means. There are alſo great irregularities in the Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Burroughs Electing as well as in the Electors: I can ſee no reaſon why <hi>Cornwall</hi> a poor and barren County ſhould return 43 Members for Parliament, and yet <hi>Cheſhire</hi> together with the City of <hi>Cheſter</hi> ſhould return in all but 3, and why old <hi>Sarum</hi> which has but 2 Houſes, and thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Commands of one Landlord, ſhould ſend 2 Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives to Parliament, whilſt many other Towns which might deſerve the Title and Priviledges of Cities ſend no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives at all. I can ſcarcely think a Parliament thus Conſtituted can truly and fairly repreſent the People, the Majority and Richeſt of them being by ſuch inequallities excluded from an Electing Vote. The ſame inconvenience ſprings from the Conſtitutions of the Boroughs which Elect, not by vertue of their Wealth, Dignity, or Number of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, but by the Burrough Houſes in which they live, Theſe only, (which perhaps are the moſt inconſiderable
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98346:13"/>part of the Burrough) having in them the Electing power excluſive of the reſt. This Qualification makes ſuch Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſell better to a purchaſer then any others in the Town, and it is cuſtomary for Gentlemen who are deſirous of a Seat in Parliament, to lay out their Mony in ſuch Bargains, and tho' it coſts them dear, yet if it be poſſible, they will be Landlords of a ſufficient number of theſe Borough Houſes, (in the purchaſe whereof ſome Friends Name is moſtly made uſe of in Truſt) that thereby they may Command an Election either for themſelves or their Aſſigns at pleaſure. What is this leſs than buying of Votes with Money? A Crime which has been always lookt upon with a ſevere brow, and yet Licens'd by this old Uſage. Nor can I diſcern why this Electing power ſhould be thus fixt to the Freehold in being, reſtrained to a ſmall and inconſiderable number of Houſes, as if Wood and Stone had a Rational faculty, and muſt be made uſe of to build and repair the Government.</p>
               <p>The Methods of Electing in theſe Boroughs are various, Titles to Elect are alſo different, and very often dubious and uncertain. This neceſſitates double Elections, and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances falſe Returns, which are often made ill uſe of; for the King having a power to nominate the Sheriff, and he to make a Return, it may happen that the true and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Members ſhall continue Petitioners only, whilſt ſuch as came in by unjuſt Returns, paſs an Act to give the King Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the maintainance of a Stranding Army. This Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice was of much uſe in the laſt Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and became ſo notorious from the great Number of Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, that a Gentleman being ask'd, whether the Houſe of Commons ſate that day in the <hi>Parliament;</hi> No, (reply'd he) It ſtood in the <hi>Lobby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is Cuſtomary in the Borough of <hi>Limmington</hi> in <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> to Elect by the <hi>Ballot:</hi> The manner is to give to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Electing Burgeſs (their number being limitted and known) a different Colour'd <hi>Ball</hi> for every <hi>Competitor,</hi> each
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98346:14"/>Colour being reſpectively appropriated to the ſeveral Competitors: As ſuppoſe there ſhould be three Candidates, each Elector has three ſeveral Balls given him, which he ſo manages as to keep only that in his hand, which by its Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour belongs to the perſon he intends to chuſe; this being inclos'd in his hand, he puts it into a cloſe Box made for that purpoſe, leaving no poſſibility to any one to detect what colour'd <hi>Ball</hi> he put into it. Thus each having put in his <hi>Ball</hi> according to his Vote, the Balls of one Colour are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from thoſe of another colour, and ſo according to the Majority of Balls of one Colour, the Return is made. This Method I know to be of great advantage where it is made uſe of; It prevents Animoſities and Diſtaſt, and very much aſſiſts that freedom which ought to be in Elections. No man in this way need fear the diſobliging of his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, Cuſtomer, or Benefactor; for it can by no means be diſcovered how he gave his Vote, if he will but keep his own counſel. If this or ſome ſuch Device were appointed to be made uſe of in every Borough over all the Kingdom, I am perſwaded it would abundantly anſwer expectation, in the many Advantages which would attend it: And perhaps it would be of equal Benefit in all other Elections, as well as in thoſe, for Members of Parliament, if the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment were ſo diſpos'd as to fill up all Vacancies, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State, by the plurality of Votes appointed to elect: And I am apt to believe that ſucceeding Ages may reduce it into a Law, that Privy Councellors ſhall be choſen by the Lords, Judges by the Gentlemen at the Bar, Biſhops by their Dean and Chapters, Miniſters by their Pariſhioners, Fellows and Maſters of Colledges by the Graduates of the ſame Colledge, Sheriffs by the Gentry of the Country, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of Truſt in the State and in the Army by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Parliament by Freeholders of 40 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> and all by the <hi>Ballott.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98346:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis much e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſier</hi> (I know) <hi>to find Faults than to mend them;</hi> and I could mention many other things of the ſame nature, the Redreſs whereof, I hope will be thought of in this great <hi>Convention,</hi> before They proceed to diſpoſe of the Crown. 'Tis an eaſier matter for a People to make ten <hi>Kings,</hi> than to unmake <hi>One,</hi> and to deck a Crown with the higheſt Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives, than to deprive it, when they are Confer'd, of the leaſt of them. If the <hi>Crown</hi> be given again with the ſame Qualifications that Other <hi>Heads</hi> wore it, It will then be exalted above the Peoples reach, without ſome ſuch aſſiſting Miracle as was lately ſhewn in favour of them. <hi>Now,</hi> to reform its Redundancies is natural, eaſie, and prudent, the Government being eſcheated to the People by the Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting it; But to offer at any ſuch Attempts afterwards, will be both unkind and imprudent, and will ſignifie no more than the chatterings of a parcel of Magpies about an <hi>Owl</hi> in her <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some Men have eſpous'd an odd and unwarrantable No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Kings Deſertion of the Government amounts to a <hi>Demiſe,</hi> or Civil <hi>Death.</hi> If this be ſo, the next Heir ought immediately to be Proclaim'd, and muſt Inherit the <hi>Crown</hi> with the ſame inſeperable Prerogatives that heretofore belong'd to it, and all Laws or Acts of Parliament made to limit and abridge them, (if Lawyers ſpeak truth) are void and null. But if the <hi>Departure</hi> of the King amounts to ſuch a deſertion as diſſolves the <hi>Government,</hi> then the Power muſt neceſſarily revert and veſt in the People, who may Erect a new <hi>One,</hi> either according to the old <hi>Modell,</hi> if they like it ſo well, or any other that they like and approve of better.</p>
               <p>Were ſuch a mighty Thing to be determin'd by my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Vote, the <hi>Government</hi> ſhould be <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and this <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> ſhould be Abſolute and Arbitrary, and the <hi>Prince</hi> ſhould be my King. 'Tis He alone who is <hi>The</hi> Man in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom</hi> in reſpect of Courage and an innate Diſpoſition to delight in the Happineſs of his People, with whom I could
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98346:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>freely and ſecurely intruſt my <hi>All:</hi> But the <hi>Honour</hi> I have for Him, runs not to His <hi>Poſterity,</hi> for as a good Man may notwithſtanding, get a Profligate Son, ſo I ſhould be loath to Repoſe ſuch a Truſt at a venture in the hands of any one whom I do not know. You have a great Work to do, and 'tis from Your Councels, that after Ages muſt date their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs or Miſery, and it therefore Obliges Your moſt Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Thoughts.</p>
               <p>I hope, Sir, you will excuſe the Liberties I have taken, in giving you ſo large a Diverſion from better Notions of your own, which I know are of an higher flight and ſwifter wing than what I can pretend to: <hi>Mine</hi> I do not impoſe, but ſubmit, as becomes</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>SIR, <hi>Your Obliged humble Servant</hi> N. T.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
